{"tossups": [{"question": "This man received a boost in the polls after he was accused of needing \u201csome kind of Gestapo\u201d to fulfill his policies. This man won an election on the slogan \u201cLet Us Face the Future\u201d and subsequently passed the National Insurance Act on the advice of the Beveridge Report. The British welfare state began under this man, who chartered the creation of the National Health Service. The Potsdam Conference was attended by, for ten points, what Prime Minister who replaced Winston Churchill at the end of World War II?", "answer": "Clement<b> Attlee</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, who gave the controversial Gazimestan speech, came to power after the \u201cRallies of Truth,\u201dwhere his supporters launched the \u201canti-bureaucratic revolution.\u201d This man\u2019s downfall began when a wheel-loader rammed a government building, giving the Bulldozer Revolution its name. In part because he failed to restrain the actions of commander Ratko Mladic, this man was indicted at the Hague, but he died of heart disease in 2006 before he could be tried. For ten points, name this president of Serbia during the Balkan Wars.", "answer": "Slobodan<b> Milosevic</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "After a meeting with Henry Morgenthau, this man produced a film based on the ideas of air superiority purported by Alexander de Seversky. This man, who hired a writing corps known as the \u201cNine Old Men,\u201dproduced a film that includes a dream sequence set in a Nazi factory and salutes to Hitler. Leopold Stokowski conducted the Philadelphia Orchestra for an animated film by, for ten points, what animator and producer of<em> Der Fuehrer\u2019s Face</em> and<em> Fantasia</em>, which star Donald Duck and Mickey Mouse?", "answer": "Walt<b> Disney</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "This ruler was adopted by the empress Ruqaiya after a soothsayer claimed he would be a great ruler. This man was forced to watch his sons fight for his kingdom at Samurgh after an illness led Dara Shikoh to be named regent. In his final years, this man was confined in the Red Fort, which he had built. This father of Aurangzeb became known for constructing a white mausoleum for his wife, Mumtaz. For ten points, name this Mughal emperor who built the Taj Mahal.", "answer": "Shah<b> Jahan</b> (accept Shahab-ud-din Muhammad<b> Khurram</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A poem set during this war describes how \u201cThe larks, still bravely singing, fly / Scarce heard amid the guns below.\u201d In a poem about this war, a man imagines a dying man\u2019s \u201changing face, like a devil\u2019s sick of sin,\u201d after describing an \u201cecstasy of fumbling\u201d after the cries of \u201cGas! GAS!\u201d A John McCrae poem about this war opens \u201cIn Flanders fields the poppies blow.\u201d For ten points, name this war, the subject of Wilfred Owen\u2019s \u201cDulce et Decorum Est,\u201d which was written while in the hospital suffering from shell shock.", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (accept the<b> Great</b> War)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "In a book focusing on this event, Rosa Luxembourg described it as a \u201ccomplete failure.\u201d John Reed\u2019s reporting on this event provided the basis for his book<em> Ten Days that Shook the World</em>. A blank was fired by the<em> Aurora</em> during an attack on the Winter Palace during this event, which occurred months after a Provisional Government was established following a similar event in February. The Bolsheviks planned, for ten points, what autumn 1917 Russian revolution?", "answer": "<b> October Revolution</b> (accept<b> Russian Revolution of 1917</b> until \u201cJohn Reed\u201d is read, and prompt after; accept<b> Bolshevik Revolution</b> until \u201cBolshevik\u201d is read, and prompt after; prompt on\u201cRussian Revolution\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This architect designed a forking glass extension for the Ordrupgaard museum in Denmark and created a pulley system to retract the fabric portion of a roof inspired by the sails of Dhow boats for the Al Janoub Stadium in Qatar. This architect designed the London Aquatics Center in her home nation and was hired to design a Central Bank building in Baghdad, her birth city, shortly before her death in 2016. For ten points, name this Iraqi-British architect, the first woman to win the Royal Gold Medal for architecture and the Pritzker Prize.", "answer": "Dame Zaha (Mohammad)<b> Hadid</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "These people offered a peace deal in which they gave up lands south of the Tugela River to lure in and massacre Piet Retief\u2019s dignitaries. That incident was avenged when these people failed to breach a<em> laager</em> fort set up by Andries Pretorius at the Battle of the Blood River. These people were led by Dingane [din-GAH-nay] and Cetshwayo [key-SHWY-oh], whose armies fought the battles of Rorke\u2019s Drift and Isandlwana against the British. For ten points, name this southern African empire that was led by Shaka.", "answer": "ama<b>Zulu</b> people", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man noted that \u201ca vast majority of mankind is entirely biased by motives of self-interest\u201d while arguing in favor of a minority veto in his posthumous<em> Disquisition on Government</em>. This architect of the Bureau of Indian Affairs declared slavery to be a \u201cpositive good\u201d during an 1837 speech to Congress. This man, angered by the 1828 Tariff of Abominations, argued in favor of nullification in an Exposition and Protest. For ten points, name this South Carolina senator and Vice President under Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "John C.<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Ga\u00a8etan Dugas, a flight attendant who was nicknamed this disease\u2019s Patient O [oh], was erroneously accused of being a North American originator of this disease. Traces of this disease\u2019s type 1 strain have been found in preserved lymph and blood samples from citizens of 1960 L\u00b4eopoldville. This disease attacks CD4+ helper T cells, weakening its host\u2019s immune system. For ten points, name this retrovirus that can cause AIDS.", "answer": "<b> HIV</b> (accept<b> Human Immunodeficiency</b> Virus; accept<b> HIV-1</b>; prompt on AIDS before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "In a book condemning this event, a thinker stated \u201cKings will be tyrants by policy when subjects are rebels from principle.\u201d Mary Wollstonecraft responded to that book condemning this event with a book defending republicanism titled<em> A Vindication of the Rights of Men</em>. Edmund Burke argued for gradual change in a book titled<em> Reflections on</em>, for ten points, what event that was triggered by the fall of the Bastille?", "answer": "<b> French Revolution</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A temple sculpture at this location consists of a pair of water mirrors intended to view the sky. The Condor Stone is located in a cave in this city where boys underwent a rite of passage during the Royal Feast of the Sun. Advanced irrigation systems in this city rely on water from the Urubamba River. This city was falsely thought to be Vilcabamba Viejo by a Yale lecturer who led an expedition here. Hiram Bingham \u201cre-discovered,\u201d for ten points, what citadel sometimes referred to as the \u201cLost City of the Incas?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Machu Picchu</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A king of this country had a vision of a cross in the sky before winning the Battle of Ourique. The bull <em>Manifestis Probatum</em> recognized Afonso I as the first king of this country. The Battle of Aljubarrota was fought in this country, after which it was ruled by the Aviz dynasty. A prince of this country sponsored voyages to West Africa, sparking the Age of Discovery. For ten points, name this Iberian country that was home to Prince Henry the Navigator.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This state was the site of the SS</b><em><b> Grandcamp</b></em><b> disaster, in which nearly 600 people died after over 4 million pounds of ammonium nitrate exploded in 1947. In April 2013, this state\u2019s</b> <b>town of West was (+)</b> <b>rocked by another ammonium nitrate explosion. A 2019 chemical</b> <b>plant explosion caused evacuations in this state\u2019s Beaumont-Port Arthur metropolitan area, on the western shores of the (*) </b> Sabine Lake near the Gulf of Mexico. For ten points, name this state where the booming petrochemical industry fueled the growth of cities like Houston.", "answer": "<b> Texas</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Ma Rulong led the Hui people during a rebellion against this dynasty before defecting to this dynasty\u2019s side. The lives of Shang Zhixin\u2019s thirty-two brothers were spared in the aftermath of Wu Sangui\u2019s uprising against this dynasty; that incident, the Revolt of the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Three Feudatories, was won by this dynasty\u2019s Green Standard Army, which mobilized</b> <b>under the command of the Kangxi Emperor. This dynasty defeated (*)</b> Li Zicheng\u2019s forces at the Battle of Shanhai Pass to end the short-lived Shun dynasty. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty founded by descendants of the Jurchen people, called Manchus.", "answer": "<b> Qing</b> [cheeng] dynasty (accept<b> Manchu</b>s before read; do not accept Qin [cheen])", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In Ephesians, one of these objects \u201cof the Spirit\u201d is listed as part of the Armor of God. While praying, Ali was assassinated in 661 with a poisoned one of these weapons. In the</b> <b>Gospels, Jesus stated that he did not come to (+)</b> <b>\u201cbring peace,\u201d but instead he brought</b> <b>one of these weapons. In a 13th century legend, a hand appears from the waters of a (*) </b>lake to catch a thrown one of these weapons. For ten points, name this type of weapon whose mythical examples include King Arthur\u2019s Excalibur and one he pulled from a stone.", "answer": "<b> sword</b>s (prompt on \u201cblade\u201d or similar generic terms, but do not prompt on \u201cdagger\u201d or similar specific terms; prompt on \u201cweapon\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This modern day country was the site of a celebrated last stand by Allan Wilson when his entire Shangani patrol was wiped out by natives. The capital of Bulawayo was captured during one of the (+) Matabele Wars in what is now this country. This modern day country came into existence fifteen years after a Unilateral (*)</b> Declaration of Independence severed ties with Great Britain under the direction of Ian Smith. The ZANU-PF party rules, for ten points, what modern African country that was formerly called Rhodesia and was led until 2017 by Robert Mugabe?", "answer": "<b> Zimbabwe</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}